<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief enquiry into leagues and confederacies made betwixt princes &amp; nations, with the nature of their obligation composed in the year 1673, when England and France were confederates in a common war against Holland, and England made a separate peace with Holland, leaving France engaged in the war / by Sr. P.M.</title>
            <author>P. M., Sr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M64</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12346546</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12346546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 640:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief enquiry into leagues and confederacies made betwixt princes &amp; nations, with the nature of their obligation composed in the year 1673, when England and France were confederates in a common war against Holland, and England made a separate peace with Holland, leaving France engaged in the war / by Sr. P.M.</title>
                  <author>P. M., Sr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alliances --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59904:1"/>
            <p>A Brief ENQUIRY INTO LEAGUES AND CONFEDERACIES Made betwixt PRINCES &amp; NATIONS, With the Nature of their OBLIGATION.</p>
            <p>Compoſed in the Year 1673. when <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were Confederates in a Common War againſt <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And <hi>England</hi> made a ſeparate Peace with <hi>Holland,</hi> leaving <hi>France</hi> Engaged in the War.</p>
            <p>By Sr. <hi>P. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Tonſon</hi> at the Judges Head in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59904:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59904:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A brief Enquiry into Leagues and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies made betwixt Princes and Nations, with the Nature of their Obligation.</head>
            <p>THat which gives the formal obligation to all Contracts both public and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, thoſe betwixt Princes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and thoſe betwixt particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is the will or aſſent of the Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting. And what the mind or meaning and intention of thoſe Perſons was at the time of their contracting, that, and no more, is the Subject matter contained in the contract. I add thoſe words <hi>no more ,</hi> becauſe in matters of Pact and Promiſe, as no Man is obliged to what he never aſſented, ſo no Man can aſſent to what he never intended.</p>
            <p>But theſe Acts of the will and mind of Men are intrinsic, ſecret, and not known, till mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted and declared by ſome outward sign, ſuch as words, which of all others are the moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and proper signification of our inward ſentiments. Now a Man having signified his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59904:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaning by his words, and thereby alſo teſtified his aſſent thereto, the obligation of his Will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes extended to comprehend, not his intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic meaning only, but his words alſo. And he is bound to the true and juſt performance of them, as they are the declarative teſtimony made by himſelf, of his inviſible, and otherwiſe unknown intention.</p>
            <p>And leaſt we ſhould ſtill be in the dark, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meaning of the very words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Reaſon dictates, that in matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract they ought to be given, and taken alſo (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out manifeſt cauſe to the contrary,) in their moſt plain and ſimple ſenſe, according to their popular uſe, and received Propriety. For Contracts and Covenants transfer a Right from one Man to another, and if every Man were left at liberty in his own cauſe, and to his own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, either to Subſtitute or Suborn what tacit meaning he pleaſes, though never ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to his words; or to affix what Senſe he will upon his words, though never ſo disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his otherways ſignified intention; theſe, and either of theſe, if admitted, would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the faith of all Contracts. Things ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated betwixt Man and Man would be under looſe uncertainties; no Mans Right could be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59904:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>known, and Controverſies would be endleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Things deſtructive to humane Society, and which introduce Confuſion into the Moral World.</p>
            <p>But ſtill tis true elſo, that a man is obliged to no more, than what his will and intention was to oblige himſelf unto; nor doe his words ſuper induce any new obligation upon him, but onely declare a former ariſing from his inward aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and conſequently extend that former Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to what is now declared. And have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to alter his ſecret meaning but onely to teſtifie it. And are not to be conſidered as disjoind from it, but conjoind with it. And if a man does not rightly expreſs what he truly means, he is unhappy therein, and it may involv him in trouble and inconvenience.<note place="margin">Quid? verbis ſatis hoc can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum erat? mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè. Quae res igitur valuit? Voluntas. Quae ſi tacitis nobis intelligi poſſet verbis omnino non uteremur, quia non poteſt, verba reperta, ſunt, non quae impedirent ſed quae indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carent vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem. <hi>Cic.</hi> Orat. prc <hi>A. Caec.</hi>
               </note> Yet if by the moſt probable conjectures it can be found, that his true meaning was different from what his words ſeemingly import, equity will relieve him, by preferring his meaning before his words. Nay if the meaning of men in their mutual Pacts and Stipulations could certainly be known without words, the ſuperaddition of words would be wholly uſeleſs and ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the Interpretation of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, that which primarily and principally is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59904:4"/>to be regarded in caſe any doubt ariſes, is, what the mind of intention of the Contractors was. And this muſt be collected from all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſigns and indications not only of words whither ſpoken or written, but of other rational Conjectures, fetch'd from their ſeveral Topics of Precedent Cauſes, concurring Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, neceſſary Conſequents or effects and the like. And where there is no Reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, nothing of abſurdity that would follow, or which admitted would render the Contract uſeleſs, we ought to ſtand to the Propriety of the words; yet ſtill with this difference, that in <hi>matters odious</hi> they ought to be reſtrain'd to their narroweſt ſignification, in <hi>matters fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable</hi> enlarged to their full latitude, in both according as the Nature of the thing, and the Equity of the caſe ſhall direct. But never to be extended to things unlawful, impoſſible, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and repugnant, abſurd and irrational. What's unlawful a man ought not to will, and if he docs, his Act morally conſidered is a nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſo not obligatory. What's impoſſible he cannot perform, and ſo in vain to will it. Contraries he cannot will at the ſame time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe repugnant. And 'tis to be preſum'd, that a man of Reaſon will not will what's irrational.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59904:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It was a manifeſt Caption and Cavil in the <hi>Romans,</hi> who being to diviee the Ships betwixt them and <hi>Antiochus</hi> by equal ſhares, cut every Ship into two equal parts.<note place="margin">Dimidia par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Navium.</note> For half the Ships, according to the uſual Propriety of the words, is not the half of every Ship cut aſunder, but half of their entire number, with reſpect firſt had to their goodneſs and dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>It was not ſaid,</hi> Non infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, <hi>but</hi> non generent bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note>After the ſecond Punic War it was Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted by League, that the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> ſhould not <hi>have</hi> or <hi>wage</hi> War with any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave of the <hi>Roman</hi> People. The word <hi>War</hi> is generical and partible into the two Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>invaſiv</hi> and <hi>defenſiv.</hi> The Queſtion is, whether in this caſe it ſhall be extended to both Species, or reſtrained only to Invaſiv. Here tis to be conſidered that the ſubject matter of the Queſtion is of a thing <hi>odious</hi> and <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome, viz.</hi> the Diminution of Liberty, both Civil and Natural. For Nature allows every man a Right of defending himſelf, by repelling force with force, and if every man, then much more a Politick Society. The Equity of thir caſe directs us to believe that the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> would not renounce ſo neceſſary a Right. The propriety of the word War is ſalv'd well enough
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59904:5"/>by reſtraining it to the Principal Species of War, <hi>viz.</hi> Invaſive, which carries with it a greater oſtentation of power than a Defenſive. Thus in a matter <hi>Odious,</hi> the Equity of the Caſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, and the Propriety of the Words ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or <hi>Waging</hi> War allowing, they ſhall be conſtrued, only to reſtrain the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> from any Hoſtile Aggreſſion or Invaſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but not from the neceſſary Defence of themſelves when attaqu'd by an Enemy.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the words of the ſaid League had been to forbid the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing or relieving any Enemy of the <hi>Roman</hi> People with Arms. Here the word <hi>Arms</hi> is likewiſe general, and may be divided into Offenſive and Defenſive. The Queſtion is, whither in this caſe it ſhall be taken general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to comprehend all Arms, or reſtrictivly to Arms offenſiv onely, which are the nobler ſort of Arms, and ſometimes the Nobler ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies is taken for the whole Genus, as in the former Caſe of <hi>War.</hi> If we proceed by the former method we ſhall find, that the matter of the Queſtion is of a thing <hi>Favourable</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificial, viz.,</hi> the hindring the Relief of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. That the intentional Equity of the Caſe is to debar an Enemy from all Inſtruments of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59904:5"/>Hoſtility, not only thoſe whoſe proper uſe is to hurt as Swords, Bows, Javelins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thoſe alſo whoſe proper uſe is to repel all Hoſtile hurt, ſuch, as Shields, Helmets, Coats of Maile or what elſe were the uſe of that Age. But ſo as not to extend the words beyond the Subject matter of Arms, to Clothes, Victuals and the like, for ſuch are not Arms, and though they repel Hurt as cold and Hunger, yet tis not Hoſtile him. And we find alſo that the propriety of the words beſt agrees here with their largeſt Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Tis clear therefore that in this Caſe <hi>the releiving of an Enemy with Arms,</hi> ſhall be understood Contrary to what in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, not reſtrictively to Arms offenſive onely, but extenſively ſo as to Comprehend all Arms whatſoever.</p>
            <p>All Leagues and Confederacies properly ſo called, made and contracted betwixt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Nations, are but the Deductions and Political Reſults of natural juſtice and Wiſdom as they are particularly applicable to the preſent Emergencies of State. Juſtice Examins their Principles, Wiſdom their Ends. So that if two or more Princes Confeder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59904:6"/>together againſt a Third, whom tehy Declare their Common Enemy, And the War ſo declared be in its Nature Manifestly unjuſt, this is an ill grounded War through defect of the Principle, and is rather a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination then a League,<note place="margin">Liga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>à ligando.</note> for every League both in name and nature implies a Tie or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, But <hi>no Prince is tied to be unjuſt.</hi> Suppoſe then the War to be as to its Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, juſt, and ſo the League initially good, yet if by the neceſſary Concomitants and Conſequents thereof it be found that in the Event it will certainly involv one of the Confederates in apparent ruin and destruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, This if continued is an ill adviſed War, and the obligation to it ceaſes through defect of the End. For <hi>no Prince is bound to deſtroy himſelf.</hi> And the proper and adequate end of all Leagues and Alliances betwixt Princes and Governments is the ſafety and benefit of each others Crown and People.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The French King declared <hi>England</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal in the War againſt <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </note>If there be Principal and Acceſſory in a War, and the Principal be ſatisfied as to the terms and conditions of Peace offered, the other Prince who is but the Acceſſory ought to acquieſce, But if both be Principals, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59904:6"/>one is free to purſue his Right though the other deſiſts.</p>
            <p>A Prince cannot oblige himſelf to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a War during the pleaſure of his Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate or which is all one, not to make a Peace without the others conſent. When I ſay <hi>he cannot,</hi> I mean not any Civil Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency or defect of power on the part of the Prince, but a moral impoſſibility or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy on the part of the thing. And if a Treaty be couch'd in ſuch like terms, they are either meerly inſignificant, or muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſome equitable conſtruction to make them reducible to a practical ſenſe. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe according to the rigour of the Letter ſuch Words would oblige a Prince to continue an unreaſonable an untimely a calamitous War, onely to gratifie the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, will, or humour of another. And this will be to tie a Prince to do what he is already tied not to do, which is a Moral Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>But put Caſe the Treaty obliges both Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to continue the War by a Conjunction of forces till both may obtain reaſonable
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59904:7"/>Conditions from their Common Enemy. In this Caſe each Prince ſhall have the Judgment not onely of his own but of the others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions alſo, ſo far forth as they relate to the continuance or diſcontinuance of the War on his part, elſe upon pretext that his Conditions are not reaſonable, the one may everlaſtingly Opiniaſtre the War and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently engage the other in it during his ſingle pleaſure.</p>
            <p>All Leagues and Contracts as well with Princes as with private Perſons are ever mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and reciprocal, and are always made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two parties at feweſt, and where there are but two in the contract, if one of them departs from it, tis no longer a contract. Now a Prince by the non performance of every material point contained in the League or Treaty violats the Faith thereof and departs from the League it ſelf. And this non performance on the part of the one Prince does not operate by way of inveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the other a power or moral faculty of breaking or nonperforming with him in a matter of the like nature; for then it would tantamount to this, becauſe one is falſe to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59904:7"/>me therefore I may be falſe to him. But it operates by way of annulling and avoiding the whole League, as having no longer any obligation in it. It becomes a meer canceld Bond, and is ſo far from being, an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that in the iſſue and effects it proves a Diſagreement,</p>
            <p>No Prince is bound by any League to periſh ſingly or in company with another, and the ſafety welfare and proſperity of his People are his Primary obligation. Firſt in Time and firſt in Dignity, to which all Treaties and Tranſactions with forrain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are but ſecondary and ſubſervient, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any of them be pleaded to evacuate that original and fundamental obligation. And though private Perſons may in ſeveral Inſtances contract to their own great Hurt and Dammage, and ſtill be bound up there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, yet tis otherwiſe with Princes in their public and politic capacities becauſe of the Conjugate Intereſt of Prince and People. Forasmuch as a Prince cannot greatly hurt himſelf without hurting them to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of whom, and to the procuring of whoſe good and benefit, he is already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingaged
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59904:8"/>In which ſenſe tis infallibly true, <hi>Actus Poſterior non praejudicat priori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Princes, in their making Leagues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies each with other, take their meaſures from the Consideration of the preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition of their Affairs in the whole complex of them both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. If the ſame reaſons and inducements remain, which firſt moved them to enter into the League, not to perſiſt in it would be levity at leaſt, and if conjoind with a deſign of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieving and hurting another no leſs then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidy. But if a new Scene of affairs opens quite different from the former, if unexpected Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents fall out which Chang the reaſon of the Caſe, ſuch, as if either of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates could have had the foreknowledg of, He would never have entered into the League. here the cauſe of it ceaſes. The foundation fails. The Prince is to conſult the preſent conjuncture, to take other meaſures ſuited and adapted to the now State of things. For to debar a Prince from accommodating his Councils to new and unforeſeen Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. is equally abſurd, as to oblige a mariner not to ſhift his ſails according to the variation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59904:8"/>of the Winds. A Prince thinks it juſt and reaſonable under his preſent circumſtances to enter into a Society of Arms with another, and be Confederate with him in a common War. The Condition of his Affairs after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards changes, and as then conſidered, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the War unreaſonable, His people fall into diſtempers at home, his Arms more requiſite elſewhere. The continuation of the War followed with a train of fatal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences at firſt not ſo eaſily diſcoverable. In this Caſe the Prince needs none to diſpenſe or abſolv him, if any other could do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Perſon contracted with, from the Tie and Bond of his Confederacy. He was never obliged under theſe Circumſtances, nothing of this caſe was included in the League, and therefore tacitly excepted; the then State and condition of his Affairs, which was the moving and leading cauſe to his conſenting to it, is now quite different and become another thing, and the former motivs to a War are now changed into more powerful arguments for a Peace.</p>
            <p>Tis the ſame in all pacts and promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt private perſons; they are all ſubject to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59904:9"/>the tacit condition of <hi>Things abiding in the ſame ſtate,</hi> Not as if humane Affairs could long abide without chang, but tis meant onely of <hi>things</hi> relating to the Pact or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſuch as contributed to the Being of it, and without which implied it had not been made.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Omnia eſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debent eadem quae fuerunt cam promitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, ut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittantis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem teneas. Quie quid m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem facit de iutegro conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lende &amp; meam fidem liberat. <hi>Sen.</hi> de <hi>Benet.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note>For Example, I promiſe my friend I will relieve him as long as I live and never ſuffer him to want. But I was then in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a plentiful fortune, am now reduced to penury, ſo that what I have, barely ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces my own neceſſities. Here my promiſe binds me not, Nature teaching and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty permitting to prefer my ſelf. Perhaps my friend becomes a Criminal to the State, and by Law, though a ſubſequent one, I am forbid to relieve him. Here my Duty to the Government forecludes my promiſe. Or if an Uſurper forbids me under Capital Penalties, though I owe him no duty of Obedience, yet ſelf-preſervation acquits me. Nor can it be ſuppoſed that I meant to oblige my ſelf to ſupply anothers wants, with the loſs or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent hazard of my own life. Perhaps I promiſed to a friend, and he afterwards
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59904:9"/>turns my enemy, and what I intended for his good he perverts to my hurt, here I may juſtly retract my abuſed benefit. Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Caſes may be framed, wherein the chang of things ſhall change the Reaſon, and conſequently the Obligation of a Promiſe. And though when I promiſed, I did not cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion expreſly againſt ſuch Accidents and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, under which I would be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not to be bound, becauſe I could not know nor foreſee them all; yet common and univerſal Reaſon ſhall be pleaded in aid of the weakneſs of my private underſtanding. For bare words ought not to be extended to over-rule the reaſon of things, but on the contrary, the reaſon of things ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the interpretation of words. And all Stipulations and contracts conſiſt as well of what is rationally implied as what is verbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed.</p>
            <p>But if Common Reaſon and equity be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaded in benefit of a private Perſon where his Life and Fortune lye at Stake, how much more ſhall it be in the Caſe of a Prince, where the Conſervation of a Community is concern'd. And if unforeſeen Accidents fall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59904:10"/>out in the ordinary Occurrences of humane Life, how much oftner in the Caſe of a War, that Grand Scene of Viciſſitudes and muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>The caſe of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> recorded in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Hiſtory, who by Surreption and not without a fraudulent Lye, obtained a League, wherein they yeilded their Perſons Slaves and Bondmen to Redeem their Lives, will, if duly examined make nothing towards the invalidating of what's before affirmed, as may to his ſaitsfaction be ſeen by him who has the leiſure to conſult <hi>Grotius</hi> in his 2d, Book <hi>de Jure Belli ac Pacis</hi> Cap. 13. <hi>Paragr.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> is Confederate with <hi>France,</hi> in a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> at the ſame time makes War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Spain,</hi> who is an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note>In Caſe two Princes be Confederates in a War againſt a third, and one of them by Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile Provocations Occaſionally ariſing from this War, or by Voluntary deſign Engages himſelf in a new War againſt a fourth Prince, who is a Friend and Allie of the other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate, to the Multiplication ſtill of more Wars by a Superfaetation. In this Caſe the ſtate of Affairs is quite altered from what it was when the League was firſt entred into, and that other Conſederate will labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59904:10"/>a double diſadvantage, For firſt, the Forces of his Confederate will by this new War be diſtracted and divided, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more of the burden and danger of the War devolv'd upon him. 2dly. The aſſiſtance which he gives his Confederate, and which is intended for maintenance of the War againſt a Common Enemy, will either wholly or in part be diverted to a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Allie; and by this means ſhall with one hand Fight againſt his Enemy, and with the other againſt his Friend. And in Caſe the Conſervation of the Amity of that Allie be of great uſe to him and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and his true Intereſt complicated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, he ſhall now become Engaged in an unnatural War againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>But put the Caſe ſtill Stronger. Suppoſe it was caution'd in the Treaty of the League, that if the War which the two Confederates were to make againſt a third Prince or State ſhould occaſion a new War againſt one of thoſe Confederate from a fourth Prince, that in ſuch Caſe both the ſaid Confederates ſhould ſtill aſſiſt each other in the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the War, and moreover declare
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59904:11"/>that fourth Prince or State their Common Enemy. Here an unforeſeen Accident or unexpected change cannot be pleaded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this new War is not onely ſuppoſed but provided againſt by expreſs Covenant.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer two ways. Firſt if one of the Confederates has already a League and Alliance with that fourth Prince , againſt whom this new War is to be undertaken, and no violation of the League on the part of that Prince, that Proviſo how expreſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is abſolutely Void. For no Prince is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged in compliance with his Word to a new Confederate to break his Faith with an old One, and where Contracts prove repugnant one to another, the firſt ſtands good, the ſecond is a nullity.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid there has been a violation of the League on the part of that Prince by his giving Aſſiſtance to an Enemy. As in the Caſe now before us, <hi>Spain</hi> aſſiſts <hi>Holland</hi> with whom <hi>England</hi> is at War. To this will be anſwered <hi>Spain</hi> aſſiſts not <hi>Holland</hi> againſt <hi>England,</hi> but againſt <hi>France.</hi> And never did any League or Treaty forbid a Prince, or can
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59904:11"/>forbid him to aſſiſt his Friend, againſt his own, and his Friend's Common Enemy, for this were utterly to ſubvert the fundamental Principels and Maxims of all Political Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, though this Accident of a new War ariſing with another Prince was ſuppoſed, yet many others as weighty as that may fall out wholly unforeſeen, for tis not poſſible for humane underſtanding to Enumerate all future Contingencies. Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the diſpoſition of a Prince's Affairs at home, the temper of his People, ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Conſiderations of a private nature and not ſit to be Publiſhed, may render a peace Abſolutely Neceſſary, of which the Prince is the ſole Judg. And if upon ſerious and mature thoughts he finds his Inducements. Real not Feigned, Weighty not Frivolous, not Levity or Inconſtancy in the Caſe, but Neceſſity, and ſuch a one as he ſuffers under, not ſought for by him to palliate a fraud. If upon ſuch Circumſtances he Treats a Peace excluſive of his Confederate, who upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice given him, refuſes to be Included, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if juſt and honorable Conditions be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59904:12"/>offered him from his Enemy, the adequate End of all juſt Arms, and which when rejected may make a War Originally juſt become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, I ſay in ſo doeing the Faith and Honour of the Prince remain unblemiſh'd. Nor is it any more Imputation to him then to the Maſter of a Ship Bound upon a Voiage, though it requires haft, not to put out to Sea when the Wind is contrary, or to put back to Port when the Storm ariſes.</p>
            <p>For no ſuppoſed Covenants, Stipulations or Conditions may be admitted to interpoſe betwixt the ſafety and welfare of a Prince or People, all ſuch are directly contrary to the Intention of the Contractors and the End of the Contract; And are nothing but Words depraved and diſtorted from their genuine meaning by the Artifice of them, who would either preſerve or aggrandiſe themſelves by anothers Ruine.</p>
            <p>And as no humane underſtanding can E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerate all future Accidents, ſo no finite being can engage its ſelf againſt all future In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, This is a task onely for Omniſcience and Omnipotence for an infinitely extended
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59904:12"/>Wiſdom, which overtakes Futurities, and for a Power Commenſurate to that Wiſdom</p>
            <p>The Honour of a Prince, which is his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſcience, is too Nice and Delicat a thing for the ungentle touch of a private hand. And tis difficult to give a particular ſolution to all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act knowledg of the Original Treaties, with their Relatives, Dependencies and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, wherein the Honour of the Prince is ſuppoſed to be concernd. But this may be confidently affirm'd, if one Prince ſhall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the obligation of his Leagues and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with forrain Nations by the Standard of his own Intereſt, and no longer abide by them then they abide that teſt; And in ſo doing juſtify himſelf by the Common Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and Uſage of the moſt Civiliſed Nations in all ages, whilſt the other is tied up to all the niceties &amp; punctilios of Words heightned by an Intereſſed Caſuiſt, this ſcrupulous Prince will be ſubjected to mighty diſadvantages, and be faſt bound when the other is loſe. Now that the Practice and uſage of Nations has been ſuch is a plentiful Topic in Hiſtory, and a larg Feild to expatiate in, It may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59904:13"/>in this place ſlightly to touch ſome few Inſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Thuan.</hi> &amp; <hi>Cambd.</hi> Ann.</note>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France</hi> made a League offenſive and defenſive with Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the States Gen. of the United Provinces, with Expreſs Covenants that no one ſhould make Peace with <hi>Spain</hi> without Conſent of both the others.</p>
            <p>The Treaty was ſolemnly ratified at <hi>Paris</hi> with many Vows and Proteſtations made by the King in the preſence of the Earl of <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Ambaſſador,</hi> and repeated in ſundry Letters under his own hand to the Queen; to whom he alſo owed a great debt of gratitude for many ſignal kindneſſes, and ſeaſonable ſupplies of Men and Moneys. Yet afterwards finding his People tired and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted with continual Wars which had laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forty Years, and having good Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions offered him from <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> he ſignifies to the Queen and <hi>States</hi> his diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a Peace. And though ſecretary <hi>Cecil</hi> from hence, and <hi>Barnevelt</hi> from the States, were ſent expreſly to him to confirm him in the League, who ſpared not to preſs home
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59904:13"/>upon him the Faith thereof, and that not without ſome ſharp expoſtulations. Yet that King excuſed himſelf by the importunity of his Affairs, proteſting, that his refuſal of a Peace with <hi>Spain</hi> would involv him in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions at home. That the Law of Nature prefer'd ſelf preſervation. That the Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will'd his Peoples good ſhould be the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Law. That Chriſtian Duty: required the ſparing of Chriſtian Bloud. And ſo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a ſeperate Treaty at <hi>Vervins</hi> and left the Queen and the <hi>States</hi> to proſecute their War againſt <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1635, began the open rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Peace made at <hi>Vervins,</hi> and War was ſolemnly proclaimed betwixt the two Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> From which time ſundry Treaties were made betwixt <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>States General</hi> for carrying on a Common War againſt <hi>Spain</hi> their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, with defences of the one to make a ſeparate Treaty without comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the other. Yet the <hi>States Gen.</hi> awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened at length to diſcern, that the Lower the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Scale was depreſſed, the higher that of <hi>France</hi> would be lifted; And that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59904:14"/>whiles they enlarged their Border upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands, They fought themſelves the nearer to <hi>France.</hi> And that as it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for them on the one ſide to maintain Banks for ſecuring their low Countries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Inundations of the Sea. ſo it was as needful for them on the other ſide to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Barriere in <hi>Flanders,</hi> interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed betwixt them and the Impetuous over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing torrent of a <hi>French</hi> Power. They at laſt embraced the Honorable and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Conditions tendred them, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded a Peace with <hi>Spain.</hi> Which though <hi>France</hi> reſented, and <hi>Monſieur Servient</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Plenipotentiary at <hi>Munſter</hi> could tel them, That though he had but one eye, he could ſee that one day they would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent it. Yet the <hi>States</hi> thought themſelves out of Pupillage, and Capable to Judg their own Concerns in the laſt reſort. Nor did they think it reaſonable that <hi>France</hi> ſhould be the ſole Arbitrator of Peace and War, not onely for themſelves, but for their Allies alſo. They did nod exclude <hi>France</hi> from the Peace, but <hi>France</hi> would not be Included. And they conceived the <hi>French</hi> King had no more reaſon to formaliſe againſt them, for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59904:14"/>Concluding a ſeparate Peace, then the <hi>States</hi> had to be offended with Him, for carrying on a ſeparate War, which, continued near twelv Years longer, down to the Treaty at the Pirenees in the Year 1659, Both had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Right of Judging and of Chuſing what they Judged their proper Intereſt And <hi>Qui jure ſuo utitur nemini facit Injuriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederic</hi> the third of <hi>Denmark</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated with the <hi>Pole</hi> and <hi>Brandenburger</hi> againſt <hi>Sueden</hi> under Strict defenſes of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into a ſeparate Treaty without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the other Allies, yet the <hi>Suediſh</hi> King having made that Miraculous March over the Frozen Seas into <hi>Zeland,</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> impelled by the Neceſſity of his affairs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that memorable Treaty at <hi>Roſchild,</hi> which under the Mediation of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> ſaved <hi>Denmark.</hi> And his Father <hi>Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiern</hi> the fourth, had done the like in the Year 1629, when worſted by the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had Confederated with the Princes of <hi>Saxony Pomeren</hi> and <hi>Mecklenburgh.</hi> In both which Caſes there was a force put, and a-Moral Neceſſity, which reſolved into this, <hi>Quicquid Cogit excuſat.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59904:15"/>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay to the aforementiond Treaty at the Pirenees, where <hi>France</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted by Article to abandon <hi>Portugal</hi> and ſend them no more ſuccours of Moneys, Men, Munition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> contrary to former Conventions with that Crown, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no Cogency of their Affairs, for they were then in a Flouriſhing Condition, but in exchang for ſeveral advantagious Conceſſions from <hi>Spain,</hi> of which when <hi>France</hi> was in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, that Article was ſoon ſuperſeded.</p>
            <p>But this is nothing to my purpoſe, Neither am I Willing to inlarge further, becauſe I did not deſign a ful Tract but onely a Brief and Modeſt Enquiry.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
